בוקר טוב, Boker tov,
so today we will be beginning מידות, Middot, which is דף ל"ד,
Daf Lamed-Daled, plus 24, but we pick up on ל"ג עמוד ב',
Lamed-Gimmel Amud Bet, the last part of תמיד. Tamid. And we basically,
if you remember where are we in the bringing of the תמיד,
Tamid, so we had the people go in, the כהנים, Kohanim, go
back in to finish the cleaning up of the מנורה Menorah and
of the מזבח Mizbeiach in the היכל, Heichal, and then we had
the burning of the קטורת. Kettores. We had a very nice little
description about how the קטורת Kettores was burned. So you have the
limbs of the תמיד Tamid put on the ramp, you have the
היכל, Heichal, actually the first עבודה Avodah done in the היכל, Heichal,
and it actually mentioned there all the people that were in at
this time did השתחויה, Hishtachavayah, prostration before they left. We also have
that very fascinating thing about the throwing of the gong or whatever
it was in that space between the אולם Ulam and the מזבח
Mizbeiach before entering in, and that sort of woke everybody up and
told them things are really about to start to get busy. All
the כהנים Kohanim started running to do their bowing down, all the
לויים Levi'im started getting ready to do their שיר. Shir. We had
the שיר Shir of the לויים, Levi'im, and now we are, so
we've done the קטורת. Kettores. And we also found out that everybody
had to leave that space, the היכל Heichal and even the space
between the היכל Heichal and מזבח Mizbeiach when the קטורת Kettores was
being brought, which is learned from יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Was הממונה
Hamemunneh allowed to be there? Well, it says לא יהא הממונה עד
שיאמר הממונה לו הקטיר. lo yei hamemunneh ad sheyomar hamemunneh lo hakteir.
And then it says פרשו העם. Pirshu ha-am. Right, so now I
understand that. So was this הממונה Hamemunneh there? Presumably not. So he
told him הקטיר. Hakteir. וכל אדם, V'chol adam, yeah, he said, do
it, and then everybody left. He gave everybody a minute or two
to leave and then presumably. So it means this guy הממונה, Hamemunneh,
also a minute or two to leave? Yeah, presumably. Unless he called
from very far away. No, so he just got out. Presumably he
left. Anyway, so now we are about to wrap up the תמיד.
Tamid. Now, I do want to say by the way
that it says that all the כהנים Kohanim ran to do their
bowing down, but
it doesn't say where did they bow down? What do you mean
they all ran to do their bowing down? When does that happen?
I mean, we just heard that the people that went into the
היכל Heichal bowed down. So according to a number of מפורשים, Meforshim,
actually what happened was that once the תמיד Tamid was brought and
these עבודות Avodos of the היכל Heichal were done and the קטורת
Kettores was done, because you're not supposed to go into the היכל
Heichal if you don't have to do an עבודה. Avodah. But once
the first עבודות Avodos were done of the morning, the תמיד Tamid
was brought and the קטורת Kettores was brought and so on, then
you could go in to do השתחויה. Hishtachavayah. And that's some understand
that at this moment, when it says the כהנים Kohanim now they
heard the gong or whatever and they all got ready to do
השתחויה, Hishtachavayah, that after the קטורת Kettores was brought, now all the
כהנים Kohanim that were going to work that day started their day,
I guess after their דאווענען, davenen, whatever, and before everything else happened,
they went in and they did השתחויה Hishtachavayah in the היכל, Heichal,
which is actually again talking about the whole issue of תפילה Tefillah
and קורבנות, Korbanos, you know, we very much associate השתחויה Hishtachavayah with
sort of תפילה, Tefillah, it's more your personal connecting to God, not
through a ritual of קורבן. Korban. So again, it is after the
תמיד, Tamid, but it is interesting, you know, that this idea that
all the כהנים Kohanim go into the inner sanctum, not the קודש
קודשים, Kodesh Kodashim, but the היכל, Heichal, and do השתחויה. Hishtachavayah. So
that was implicit in the previous משנה Mishnah but not spelled out.
Right, the holiness felt to the ארון. Aron. Yeah, the sense of
God's presence. I believe the sense that, you know, God is שוכן,
Shochein, right, so there's the שכינה Shechinah is present in the היכל
Heichal and particularly over the ארון. Aron. That's the sense, you know,
that this so, yeah. I'm sorry, when was this השתחויה? Hishtachavayah? It
doesn't say. Just says when, when. Presumably after the קטורת Kettores was
done, but that's speculation, that's what מפורשים Meforshim say. Okay. So when
it says sort of like a preview then, right? It says they
all ran to do השתחויה Hishtachavayah after the קטורת Kettores presumably. Right,
so now let's take a look, but we also mentioned the לויים
Levi'im doing their שירה, Shira, and we haven't discussed and that's going
to be discussed now in this פרק. Perek. So let's take a
look now top of ל"ג עמוד ב'. Lamed-Gimmel Amud Bet. בזמן שכהן
גדול נכנס להשתחוות, Bezman shekohen gadol nichnas l'hishtachavos,
now, when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol would go in to do
השתחויה, Hishtachavayah, so this already we mentioned all the כהנים, Kohanim, we're
not going to discuss that, but we were going to talk about
what happens when it was the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But then,
the same way we also discussed what happens when the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol wants to do the קטורת. Kettores. So the reason we're
pointing this out is presumably sometimes, like he, you know, he would
make a point of doing these things. So if he wanted, if
he was going in to do the השתחויה, Hishtachavayah, שלושה אוחזים בו,
shlosha ochezim bo, three people would hold on to him. אחד בימינו
ואחד בשמאלו, Echad biyemino v'echad bismolo, one on his right, one on
his left, like he had a whole retinue obviously for כבוד, Kavod,
ואחד באבנים טובות, v'echad b'avanim toivous, one in precious stones. So I've
seen some pictures of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, so right, some
assume well, where are the precious stones? They're on the, you know,
they're on the shoulders of the אפוד. Ephod. So what does it
mean? Like holding onto them? Like so why do you need someone?
Or it could be the חושן. Choshen. Oh no, some, oh I
see. Yeah, it could be. So what, so what, so what does
that mean? Do you need help because it's so heavy? Maybe. That's
heavy maybe. Anyway, I've definitely seen some pictures. I don't know whether
where they're from but whatever, that actually had somebody walking in front
holding like two precious stones, you know, so that sort of like
you know how like so you can't see how that's like a
כבודיק kavodik thing. Like this person is surrounded by people and by
jewels. Was it just only just two stones? I don't know. I
don't know. Anyway, I don't know if it was a Jewish picture
or not. I mean, I think it was a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, I don't know. Could it be they attached it behind him?
Yeah, that's what some people say. Like, grasping to the אבני שהם?
Avnei Shoham? I know, it's very odd. Yeah. So, again, I don't
know. Okay. Wasn't doing
the עבודה Avoda yet. Maybe this was heavy to wear, maybe. Yeah,
that's sort of like what Michael was saying. Wearing the אפוד. Ephod.
But he had one on each shoulder. He had men on each
side too. Maybe he wasn't wearing the אפוד. Ephod.
He wasn't wearing the אפוד? Ephod? No. כהן גדול Kohen Gadol being...
he wasn't wearing בגדי כהונה? Bigdei Kehuna? Well, I mean, you can't
be נכנס nichnas to the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash without בגדי כהונה.
Bigdei Kehuna.
Well maybe when he was walking around and not actually doing the
עבודה, Avoda, maybe he was too heavy to wear and he had
a cup
bearer carrying it around for him when he was to do the
עבודה. Avoda. But I don't know. Yeah, I don't know. I mean,
we only... we would have... I think we would have had that
description. Anyway, and then why would it have just mentioned אבנים טובות
avanim tovos and not, you know, more specifically the אפוד, Ephod, the
חושן? Hoshen? Anyway, כיון ששמע את קול רגליו של כהן גדול, keivan
sheshama es kol raglav shel Kohen Gadol,
when he heard the approaching of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, the
sound of his feet. Going through the מעיל, me'il, the פעמונים. pa'amonim.
Yeah, exactly. And although... interesting why didn't it say the פעמונים, pa'amonim,
but anyway, he heard him approaching.
שהוא יוצא, shehu yotzei, that he was leaving, presumably leaving the היכל.
Heichal. He was done with his השתחויה. hishtachavaya. He went in first.
He went in first. הגביה לו את הפרוכת. higbi'ah lo es ha-paroches.
Oh, you see, okay, I misspoke before. Anyway, because it is about
to say the other כהנים Kohanim did. הגביה לו את הפרוכת, higbi'ah
lo es ha-paroches, he lifted up the curtain. What curtain? So presumably
we're going to find out there's a curtain over the opening of
the אולם. Ulam. No, the אולם Ulam was that hall before the
היכל. Heichal. So he lifted up the curtain. First?
It's the... it's the opening here of the אולם. Ulam. Oh, there.
It's between the אולם Ulam and the outside. Okay. So he would
lift up the curtain, or maybe move it aside, lift it up.
נכנס והשתחוה ויצא, nichnas vehishtachaveh veyatza, and he would go in, because
now if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol did it, that... again, there's
a question how to read this, but one way of reading this
is, so now the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does it, he goes
now, the ממונה, Memuneh, השתחוה ויצא, hishtachaveh veyatza, and he did his
השתחויה. hishtachavaya. Then נכנסו אחיו הכהנים השתחוו ויצאו, nichnasu echav ha-Kohanim hishtachavu
veyatze'u, and then everybody, all the other כהנים Kohanim went and did
it. So actually I misspoke before, it does actually mention it here,
does it... that all the כהנים Kohanim did it, it does it
in the context of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, but it's presumably
even without the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol it's indicating that the כהנים
Kohanim would do a השתחויה hishtachavaya at this stage. Some say it
doesn't mean that the ממונה Memuneh would go separate. It means... it
means it's going back and saying that after the כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol was נכנס והשתחוה, nichnas vehishtachaveh, then everybody else did it. It's
a little redundant. Well, the way I read it is that we...
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol hasn't yet... he can't be נכנס והשתחוה
nichnas vehishtachaveh yet but then it says כיון ששמע את קולו היוצא.
keivan sheshama es kolo hayotzei. שהוא יוצא. shehu yotzei. Well, that's in
parentheses. No, no, no, the second one is. It says when he
heard the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was leaving. Anyway, okay. That's... so
anyway the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol if he was there would do
השתחויה, hishtachavaya, then everybody else would do a השתחויה, hishtachavaya, and that's
why I said all the כהנים... Kohanim... so like I said I
misspoke before it does say it here that they did the השתחויה,
hishtachavaya, all the כהנים Kohanim would get ready, they heard the gong,
and now they did the השתחויה hishtachavaya after the קטורת. ketores. In
the אולם Ulam or in the היכל? Heichal? In the היכל. Heichal.
היכל. Heichal. Like they lift up the curtain on the היכל Heichal
of the אולם Ulam and then everybody would go in. Now באו
ועמדו על מעלות האולם. ba'u ve'amdu al ma'alos ha-Ulam. Now everybody's done
their השתחויה. hishtachavaya. Now they came out and they stood on the
steps leading up to the אולם. Ulam. If you look here at
Michael's picture, right?
So... here's the curtain, they went through here, they went into the
היכל, Heichal, they did their השתחויה. hishtachavaya. Now they came out and
they're standing on these steps. Okay. And any guesses what they're going
to do on this step? Sing.
No, well, this is the כהנים, Kohanim, so what else? ברכת כהנים.
Birkas Kohanim.
Interestingly, this is called the דוכן duchan and this is not where
the כהנים Kohanim stood, this is where the לויים Leviyim stood to
do their שירה. shira. Okay, but this is where the כהנים Kohanim
are going to stand to do their ברכה. bracha. And by the
way, if you think about in שמיני Shmini what it talks about
after the dedication, right? אהרן Aharon goes into אהל מועד, Ohel Moed,
ויצא, vayeitzei, and as he leaves אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, ויברך את
העם. vayevarech es ha-am. And according to the... whatever, the... you know,
the מדרש, Midrash, the חז"ל, Chazal, that's ברכת כהנים. Birkas Kohanim. So
they all go into the היכל, Heichal, they ויצא, vayeitzei, and then
they ויברך את העם. vayevarech es ha-am. There's a parallel to what
happens in שמיני. Shmini. That's assuming they're giving it to a bystander
here. I mean where are the ישראל? Yisrael? Yeah, they stand... I
mean even if the ישראל Yisrael was there, it's not like they
could see them. Well wait, even if they... I'm going to talk
about that in a minute. They presumably... no, this is where the
לויים Leviyim would be,
this is where the כהנים Kohanim would be. So yeah, see them,
whatever
it was. Was this higher up than... These were steps. No, I
don't mean here, but I mean is this whole section higher up
than that? Than this? Yes. We'll talk about that in just back
of מידות. Middos. Because you have all these steps. Exactly. So they
could see them also that way. Oh,
that's true. That's a good point. Okay, so באו ועמדו על מעלות
האולם. ba'u ve'amdu al ma'alos ha-Ulam. So they stood by the steps
of the אולם. Ulam. עמדו ראשונים לדרום אחיהם הכהנים. amdu rishonim ladorom
acheihem ha-Kohanim. So the first people, the people that did the עבודה,
avoda, not just the השתחויה hishtachavaya in the... in the היכל, Heichal,
which was the people that cleaned the מזבח, mizbeiach, the מנורה, menorah,
the מזבח, mizbeiach, that did the קטורת, ketoret,
so they stood to the south, okay, of the steps. I really
don't know. But that's where they stood. That's maybe it was a
convention, I'm not sure. But anyway, they stood to the south of
the steps. Because they were doing stuff on the מזבח, mizbeiach, so
they're going to be closer to where they was? I don't know.
Anyway, they stood to the south of the steps. וחמישה כלים בידם
vachamisha keilim beyadam
and those who were doing it have the still the five כלי
המקדש kelei hamikdash in their hand. הטני ביד אחד, hateni beyad echad,
the basket which one of them had, the gold basket which had
the ashes from the מזבח mizbeiach from the gold altar. והכוז ביד
אחד vehakuz beyad echad and the pitcher which had all of the
stuff that they cleaned out of the מנורה. menorah. והמחתה ביד אחד,
vehamachta beyad echad,
the shovel, the gold shovel the other one had which was for
the embers. והבזך ביד אחד vehabazach beyad echad
and the, you know, the small pot we've been calling it, gold
pot which one had which had the קטורת ketoret in it. והכף
וכיסויה ביד אחד vehakaf vechisuyah beyad echad and the larger pot with
its cover in the other person's hand. Right? Remember we had all
those different tasks? So five people, five כלים, keilim, they all came
out, they stood on the right. Okay. And then everybody else presumably
after they went in and did their השתחויה, hishtachavaya, they came out
and they stood with them. וברכו את העם ברכה אחת. uverchu et
ha'am bracha achat. Now they gave one ברכה. bracha. Now what do
you mean, ברכה אחת? bracha achat? We call it three ברכות. brachot.
But it's, well, yes, I mean, it's three פסוקים, pesukim, but as
we're going to read, they did not say אמן amen between the
three פסוקים. pesukim. So they said all three פסוקים pesukim without any
interruption, without any אמן amen breaking it, so it was called here
ברכה אחת. bracha achat. So this is when they gave the ברכת
כהנים. birkat kohanim. Apparently, they didn't necessarily need to use their hands
because they're holding these things. Well, that's an interesting question. I mean,
we're going to talk about them using their hands. It doesn't say
that they put down the vessel. That's a good question, I don't
know. אלא שבמדינה, ela shebamadina, when they do ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim
outside the מקדש, Mikdash, אומרים אותה שלוש ברכות, omerim otah shalosh brachot,
you break it up into three because you say אמן amen between
each one. ובמקדש ברכה אחת, uvamikdash bracha achat, in the מקדש Mikdash
you said it without interruption, without any אמן amen breaking it, so
it was effectively one ברכה. bracha. במקדש היו אומרים את השם ככתבו,
bamikdash hayu omerim et hashem kichtavo, when they said the ברכת כהנים
birkat kohanim in the מקדש Mikdash they said God's name as it's
written, the ineffable name of God, well, not ineffable because they actually
effable it, whatever that is. Anyway, they said it. But okay, anyway,
they said God's name as it was written. ובמדינה בכינויה, uvamedina bechinuya,
and in the מדינה medina they say it the way it is
sort of, you know, stated, said, not the way it's written. The
way we say it. The way we say it, right. אדון, Adon,
you know. במדינה הכהנים נושאים את ידיהם כנגד כתפיהם, bamadina hakohanim nose'im
et yedeihem keneged kitfeihem, in the מדינה medina when they would do
נשיאת כפיים nesiat kapayim their arms would be, their hands would be,
you know, sort of at height, at shoulder height, straight out. ובמקדש
על גבי ראשיהם, uvamikdash al gabei rasheihem, and in the מקדש Mikdash
it would be, you know, up by their heads like that. Right?
Why? Because the according to the idea was that God's presence was
somehow in the מקדש, Mikdash, God's presence was resting over the hands
of the כהנים. kohanim. So therefore you don't want to be on
top of, you know, higher than where God's presence is. So you
have God's presence, it's a little anthropomorphic, but okay. Anyway, that's what
it's symbolic about, symbolically. So you don't want your head to be
higher than God, then the then the sense that the שכינה שרויה
shechina sheruya on top of the hands in the מקדש, Mikdash, you
don't want your hands to be lower than any part of your
body. But in the, but outside we don't say that in the
מדינה. medina. They give a ברכה bracha but we don't say שכינה
שרויה. shechina sheruya. Okay. They do. That's why you can't look at
the כהנים. kohanim. That's the מנהג. minhag. That's how, it's really a
מנהג minhag of, but it's a מנהג minhag of זכר zecher of
the reality in the מקדש, Mikdash, not that we actually say that
that reality is present, you know, when it's outside of the מקדש.
Mikdash. Okay. חוץ מכהן גדול שאין מגביה ידיו למעלה מן הציץ, chutz
mikohen gadol she'ein magbia yadav lema'ala min hatzitz, but the כהן גדול
kohen gadol doesn't have to bring his hand higher than the ציץ
tzitz because ultimately the ציץ tzitz is קודש להשם, kodesh l'hashem, so
it's basically not an idea that his head is above the where
the שכינה's shechina present, the קודש להשם kodesh l'hashem is there, that's
already also at the top of his head, so that somehow satisfies
that. So at that level. Right. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
or top of forehead level. רבי יהודה אומר אף כהן גדול מגביה
ידיו למעלה מן הציץ, Rabbi Yehuda omer af kohen gadol magbia yadav
lema'ala min hatzitz, even the כהן גדול kohen gadol has to, שנאמר,
shene'emar, and let's see what this has to do with, Rabbi Yehuda
sometimes goes back on the whole משנה. Mishnah. וישא אהרן את ידיו
אל העם ויברכם, vayisa aharon et yadav el ha'am vayivarkhem, he lifted
up his hands and he blessed them. And there we learn, you
know, now of course why do you need that? We learn ברכת
כהנים birkat kohanim from כה תברכו את בני ישראל. koh tevarachu et
bnei yisrael. But it could be that from here we learn the
idea of ברכת כהנים birkat kohanim immediately following going into the היכל,
Heichal, because this is exactly, right, the context. I mean, really, it
is very powerful when you see how this is sort of duplicating
what what what happened, right? So they did, right, it says, so
actually, I just said that and it's actually here not exactly identical,
because first they bring all the קרבנות korbanot and then it says
וישא אהרן את ידיו אל העם ויברכם וירד מעשות החטאת והעולה והשלמים.
vayisa aharon et yadav el ha'am vayivarkhem vayered measot hachatat veha'olah vehashelamim.
So there he actually was outside. So there they go in and
then they come out and they give a ברכה. bracha. So it's
actually not exactly parallel because the ברכת אהרן birchat Aharon actually was
not the going in and coming out, it was just after he
did the עבודה. avoda. Anyway, we do learn aspects of ברכת כהנים
birchat kohanim from that פסוק. pasuk. So here you have that after
they did the תמיד tamid and the קטרת, ktoret, the כהנים kohanim
went in, did their השתחויה, hishtachavaya, came out, stood on the steps
and did the ברכת כהנים. birchat kohanim. So clearly by this stage,
the people are already in the עזרה. azara. So the question is
when did they come in? And that's never stated anywhere. So I
want to read the next משנה mishna because we've always been talking
about when do they open the doors for everybody else and I'll
talk to you a little bit about some research I did yesterday
about that. Yes. So you're saying the כהן גדול kohen gadol has
a separate blessing in addition to what other... No, no, no, in
the story there in שמיני Shmini it was the כהן kohen got...
it was אהרן, Aharon, but... right, not as a general rule. Okay,
so let's take a look now at משנה ג. mishna gimmel. One
second, I just remembering we said that there were whatever it was
like eight or eleven שלחנות, shulchanot, right? Yeah. So but then they...
מזבח mizbeach of שלמה, Shlomo, did he have like a whole row
of them? Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're jumping back. The מפרשים mefarshim point
that out, but they say first those weren't used for anything. Those
were decorative. בזמן שהכהן גדול רוצה להקטיר. bizman shehakohen gadol rotze lehaktir.
Now, when the כהן גדול kohen gadol because we had mentioned the
כהן גדול kohen gadol wanting to do השתחויה, hishtachavaya, we're going back
a little bit because we had mentioned the הקטרה. haktara. So when
the כהן גדול kohen gadol wanted to do the הקטרה, haktara, היה
עולה בכבש. haya oleh bacheves. Excuse me. No, I'm sorry, certainly in
the morning. Okay, this is not the הקטרה haktara of the קטרת.
ktoret. This is the הקטרה haktara meaning we're now at the second
stage. We've done the burning of the קטרת. ktoret. We've done the
ברכת כהנים. birchat kohanim. And now we have to finish the תמיד.
tamid. We have all of the limbs that are halfway up the
ramp, we gotta get them up and we have to burn them.
So that's being מקטיר maktir the איברים. evarim. That's offering up, burning
the limbs. So that's the stage we're at now, the burning of
the limbs. This is finally the end of the תמיד tamid and
the end of the מסכת. masechet. So because we're mentioning a כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, we're also mentioning him here again, presumably sometimes he
would... he would make a... he would opt to do this. So
we're going to point out how they would handle it. בזמן שהכהן
גדול רוצה להקטיר. bizman shehakohen gadol rotze lehaktir. When the כהן גדול
kohen gadol wanted to be מקטיר maktir the איברים, evarim, היה עולה
בכבש, haya oleh bacheves, which is now the final thing to be
done, היה עולה בכבש, haya oleh bacheves, he'd go up the ramp
והסגן בימינו. vehasgan bimino. And he would have his assistant כהן, kohen,
his vice-כהן גדול. kohen gadol. This is the person who would take
his place if anything would happen to him. Anyway, he would be
there on the right. So this time you only have one guy?
One, instead of three. Exactly. Now, הגיע למחצית הכבש. higia lemachatzit hacheves.
They got halfway of the ramp. אחז הסגן בימינו והעלהו. achaz hasgan
bimino vehe'alehu. So it's a little bit, I mean, I don't know
if there's a hidden or not-so-hidden criticism here because we're going to
find out in a minute that he didn't even bring the limbs
up the ramp. I mean, you know, he wasn't in shape. And
that wouldn't be כבוד kavod presumably to, you know, take these big
pieces of meat. But not only did he not bring the limbs
up, he actually couldn't make it the whole way up the ramp
without some help. I can really identify. I need to go to
the gym more. Sometimes I go up two flights of stairs and
I'm winded. So actually, the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, he's halfway up
the ramp, he needs help getting the rest of the way up
the ramp. Okay? So, anyway, so the סגן sgan would help him
up the rest of the way up the ramp. והכהן גדול, ve
hakohen gadol, I mean, some of them may be in better shape.
This is the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. I know, but some of
the כהנים גדולים. kohanim gedolim. But, yeah, they often... there was a
statement in... Yes, well, as we know, the רבנים rabbanim were not
so happy about the כהנים גדולים kohanim gedolim of the בית שני.
Bayit Sheni. They were paid-for political positions and they were often people
that were pretty unlearned and, you know, had not really, you know,
worked hard. They weren't the שטארקער starker workers of the בית המקדש.
Beit HaMikdash. So, okay, so it's very common that you have a
כהן גדול kohen gadol that's... that isn't in shape and doesn't... has
never really done any real work in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
and needs help. It's not always the case, but apparently this was
often enough that they used it to describe the norm. Okay. So,
anyway, והושיט לו הראשון. ve'hoshit lo harishon. Now, how's he going to
get the pieces of meat? So the other כהנים kohanim who either
the same who got them halfway or another group based on which
position you held by were going to be the ones to take
them all the way up the ramp. Without the כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, they would have taken up the ramp and they would have
put it on the fire. With the כהן גדול, kohen gadol, they're
doing the heavy work, they're taking it up the ramp and then
they're giving it to him and he throws out the first pitch.
He... go ahead, he throws them on the fire. So, okay, so
where were we? והושיט לו הראשון. vehoshit lo harishon. So the first
person hands him, after bringing it up the rest of the way,
הראש והרגל, harosh veharegel, the head and the foot. וסמך עליהם. vesamach
aleihem. He does סמיכה. smicha. Now, that's a... זה זר. zeh zar.
You'd go and say you never do סמיכה smicha on a dead
animal. Okay. So this is all a way of כבוד kavod to
the כהן גדול kohen gadol or maybe showing, you know, he's connecting
to it because obviously he didn't do any other part of it.
So he does סמיכה, smicha, some form of giving him some connection
or honor. It's symbolic, but it's just symbolic. Yeah, totally symbolic. וזרקן.
vezarkan. And then he throws them on the fire. By the way,
we throw it on the fire rather than placing it because we
learned from זריקת הדם. zrikat hadam. the second guy was the one
who would have carried the two hands. He gives it to the
first guy, the two hands, forearms. נתן לכהן גדול וסמך עליהם וזרקן.
Netan leKohen Gadol vesamach aleihem vezarkan. And then כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
סמיכה smicha throws it on the fire. נשמט השני והלך לו. Nishmat
hasheni vehalach lo. And then the second guy leaves and he goes.
וכך היו מושיטין לו שאר כל האיברים. Vecha hayu moshitin lo shear
kol ha'eivarim. And the first guy is always there. Right. It sounds
like the first guy there's always like a little a chain. At
least three gives it to one who gives it to the כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. Four gives it to one who gives it to
the, you know, that's what it sounds like, correct. But if everybody
weren't there, then just one would go, throw it, go down, and
two would go. Presumably. Yeah, yeah, exactly. I assume the reason you
kept number one up there is maybe again, it's not so כבודיק
kovodik for the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol to have the people standing
next to him constantly like leaving. This guy leaves, next guy comes,
this guy leaves. No, there's one guy here, he gets it from
these people who are more invisible to the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
and he hands it to the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. It's much
more respectful, you know, in terms of that space. Okay. So then,
וכך היו מושיטין לו שאר כל האיברים Vecha hayu moshitin lo shear
kol ha'eivarim and that's the way they did with all the other
people. והוא סומך עליהם וזרקן Vehu somech aleihem vezarkan and he put
his hands on them and threw them on the fire. ובזמן שהוא
רוצה הוא סומך ואחרים זורקין. Uvizman shehu rotze hu somech ve'acherim zorkin.
Now if he wanted to, like he was really not in the
business it sounds like, he would just do the סמיכה smicha and
let maybe the סגן sgan or somebody else throw it on the
fire. Maybe he didn't want to get greasy at all, maybe he
would try to throw it on the fire and it wouldn't even
go to the right place. So if he wants, he could let
somebody else throw it and he'll just put his hands on it.
Okay. בא לו להקיף את המזבח. Ba lo lehakif et hamizbeach. Now
he has to walk around the מזבח. mizbeach. Obviously if the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol isn't there, Michael is right, it doesn't spell it
out, but implicit, the כהנים kohanim themselves, number one would take his
part up, throw it, number two would take his part up, throw
it and so on. Now they have to come down from the
מזבח. mizbeach. So this is the general rule, this is where we
by the way we get for like things like הושענות Hoshanos or
when the כלה kallah walks around the חתן chosson that you always
go you always go counterclockwise. You always go to your right. And
the reason and that's the basic הלכה, halacha, כל פינות שאתה פונה
לא יהו אלא לימין. kol pinot she'ata poneh lo yehu ela leyamin.
So if you're standing facing the center of where you are and
you're moving to your right, you're moving counterclockwise. So the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol would go up here, he would he would come to
this corner which was right by the big pyre where they would
throw it and then you would go all the way around like
this and come down. Right. So traffic would be on the right.
All right. This is a traffic circle here. Traffic would be on
the right. All right. So anyway, let's read the משנה. Mishnah. בא
לו להקיף את המזבח. Ba lo lehakif et hamizbeach. מהיכן הוא מתחיל?
Meheichan hu matchil? Where do you begin? קרן דרומית מזרחית. Keren dromit
mizrachit. You start at the southeast, right, where that's where the big
fire is. מזרחית צפונית. Mizrachit tzonit. You go to the northeast. So
it's basically what I showed you, you know, you're going to southeast,
northeast, that's northwest. Okay. צפונית מערבית, Tzfonit maaravit, northwest, מערבית דרומית Maaravit
dromit and southwest. Okay. So you would go around the circle. Now,
נתנו לו יין לנסך. Natnu lo yayin lenasech. Now we're still with
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol because you do the ניסוך המים nisuch
hamayim on סוכות Sukkos and ניסוך היין nisuch hayayin every day with
the קרבנות, korbanot, the wine pouring over here in this southwest corner.
Okay. And they go through they go through little funnels. They go
the funnel goes on to the top of the מזבח mizbeach and
from there it goes down other funnels and goes down underneath the
מזבח mizbeach and so on. Now these little holes here. Yes. Okay.
Okay. Fine. Anyway, so they gave him the wine. והסגן עומד על
הקרן והסודרין בידו. Vehasgan omed al hakeren vehasudarin beyado. Now the assistant
was on the corner and he had he had flags in his
hand, literally like handkerchiefs, but you know sort of like you know
signal flags as we're gonna see in a minute. Okay. We we
have this discussion in other places like when they were saying הלל
Hallel in a huge synagogue and nobody knew when to answer, they
would wave flags, right. Exactly. Exactly. Form of non-verbal communication from a
distance. Okay. So he has the flags. Now there would be somebody
with flags even if it wasn't a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, we're
going to see, because the people on the floor needed to know
when the wine was being poured and we'll see why in a
minute. So whether there is or is not a כהן גדול, Kohen
Gadol, there's going to be somebody with flags here. נתנו לו יין.
Natnu lo yayin. Where was... okay. שני כהנים עומדים על שלחן החלבים.
Shnei kohanim omdim al shulchan hachalavim. Two כהנים kohanim were standing by
the fat table. What is the fat table? You remember that there
were two tables here. One for putting the one for putting the
what do you call it the all the כלים. kelim. Actually I
read in one of the מפרשים, mefarshim, we said one for putting
you know the כלי שרת. klei sharet. I said it was well
maybe you put it down if you're tired, but somebody else indicates
that no, actually it was sort of like your workbench, like you
know they had all the כלי שרת klei sharet laid out there.
So you needed something, you know you came and you took what
you needed, maybe there'd be somebody nearby that would watch the one
you had just used. Anyway there would be the other one in
which they in which they would put the fats of stuff that
they had not yet brought up to the מזבח. mizbeach. So that's
the שלחן החלבים. shulchan hachalavim. So they were standing over there. That's
the space בין האולם ולמזבח, bein ha'ulam velamizbeach, right, that's to the
south. That's for the תמיד, tamid, other types of things, all through
the process. Anyway, so they would stand over there in that space
between the אולם ulam and the מזבח. mizbeach. שני כהנים Shnei kohanim
עומדים על שלחן החלבים. omdim al shulchan hachalavim. שתי חצוצרות בידיהם. Shtei
chatzotzrot biyadeihem. They had חצוצרות, chatzotzrot, they had trumpets. Okay, you know,
like it says in במדבר, Bamidbar, you should have trumpets, and I'll
talk about that in a minute. They had two trumpets. תקעו והריעו
ותקעו. taku veheriu vetaku. So now when they saw, so they would
do, they saw he was about to do the pouring of the
wine, they did תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, which is basically
getting everybody waking up and getting them ready. באו ועמדו אצל בן
ארזא. bau veamdu eitzel Ben Arza. They went and they stood next
to Ben Arza. We said before that Ben Arza was על הצלצל.
al hatzeltzel. He was over some musical instrument. This is all sort
of again to alert people, particularly the לויים, Levi'im, that they're about
to start doing the music, okay. אחד מימינו ואחד משמאלו, echad miyemino
ve-echad mismolo, one of them on his right, one of them on
his left. שחה לנסך. shacha lenaseich. Now the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
or whoever was about to pour the wine bent down to do
the wine. So he saw they were ממש mamash about to pour
the wine. והניף הסגן בסודרים, vehenif hasgan besudarim, so you waved the
flags, he gave the sign. He's doing, he's about to do the
ניסוך היין. nisuch hayayin. והקיש בן ארזא בצלצל. vehekish Ben Arza batzeltzel.
Ben Arza would make the sound with the צלצל, tzeltzel, he says
it's maybe like it's maybe a triangle or something, you know, or
a gong or something, but everybody knows now is the time, he's
about to do the pouring of the wine. ודברו הלויים בשיר vedibru
haLevi'im beshir and the לויים Levi'im open literally spoke in song. Now
we often when we think about the לויים, Levi'im, we think about
the musical instruments. Okay, there's actually a discussion, right, whether עיקר שירה
בפה ikar shirah be-peh or עיקר שירה בכלי, ikar shirah bikhli, whether
the primary thing is the singing and the musical instruments are just
the accompaniment or vice versa. The fact that it says דברו בשיר
dibru beshir certainly emphasizes the verbal singing. Now the לויים Levi'im were
here on this דוכן. duchan. Okay, that's where the לויים Levi'im were,
which is interesting. This was going on here, right? See, this guy
was waving, the כהנים kohanim were here, so Ben Arza must have
been, I imagine, somewhere around here so that the לויים Levi'im would
be able to, but maybe not, maybe they could just hear the
gong. But wherever Ben Arza was, he clanged the thing, as he
was about to pour, then the לויים Levi'im all opened up into
song. Let me understand, he gave him the נסכים nesachim after he
did the circle around? No, he did the circuit, he's standing at
this corner. Let me understand, then he gave him the נסכים. nesachim.
And when he's about to do the pouring, he's bending down and
they see he's about to, then they, when he's sort of standing
and he's at the location, they do the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah
teruah tekiah. Then those two כהנים kohanim go to Ben Arza wherever
he stands. Then they see by the flags that the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol is literally bending down and about to pour. He clangs
with the bell or whatever it is and the לויים Levi'im start
singing. All right. Okay, והקיש בן ארזא בצלצל ודברו הלויים בשיר. vehekish
Ben Arza batzeltzel vedibru haLevi'im beshir. Now why do they only start
singing now? I mean you did זריקת הדם, zerikat hadam, you burnt
איברים, evarim, why only singing now? So here's a very important principle
which is אין שירה אלא על היין, ein shirah ela al hayayin,
which the גמרא Gemara learns out, right, it says actually in that
famous מדרש Midrash in where is it, in שופטים, Shoftim, right, you
remember where all of the trees try to elect the king, and
anyway they go to the various, you know, they go to the
olive tree and they go to the vine. Basically the only person
who wants to be king is the one who's worthless. But anyway,
that's a different story. That's the מדרש. Midrash. But in that metaphor,
not מדרש, Midrash, that's the metaphor. In that metaphor, they basically the
vine says, you know, why should I be king? You know, I
make wine that's משמח לבב אנשים, mesameiach levav anashim, you know, and
so on, that makes people happy. And I, does it say there
the שיר, shir, maybe I'm confusing it with something. Anyway somewhere, that's
יין שמחה yayin simcha association. Anyway somewhere there's also the association, I'm
sorry I don't remember the פסוק pasuk right now or the גמרא,
Gemara, but anyway right there's the association of wine with שירה, shirah,
with song. And also because you know wine is joyful and it
has those associations. So because of that idea that there's a שירה,
shirah, the חז"ל Chazal understood, or it was understood even you know
it was already understood you know very early on, that that was
associated with the pouring of the wine on the מזבח. mizbeiach. So
although the whole קרבן korban had been brought and the only thing
that had not been done was the pouring of the wine, they
waited for the שירה shirah for the ניסוך היין. nisuch hayayin. Now
because of that by the way is why we do קידוש Kiddush
on wine, because of אין שירה אלא על היין. ein shirah ela
al hayayin. And just while we're mentioning that, you know, I mean
obviously the ritual significance of wine is the whole thing, we're talking
about יין לנסך, yayin lenaseich, right, we all know about the איסור
issur of יין נסך, yayin nesech, right, of non-Jewish wine because of
the ritual power of wine being poured. But it's also why we
have it and I should also mention that most of the things
we do על הכוס, al hakos, other than קידוש Kiddush and הבדלה,
Havdalah, are not in the גמרא. Gemara. For example the ברכה berachah
by a ברית מילה bris milah that we do על הכוס, al
hakos, the ברכה berachah we do at a wedding על הכוס. al
hakos. None of those things are in the גמרא, Gemara, but they
got introduced relatively early on because they, as we know, they give
it a lot of ritual significance when you do it over a
cup of wine. So that idea of אין אומרים שירה אלא על
היין ein omrim shirah ela al hayayin is a very powerful one
and that's why they waited till now to do the שירה. shirah.
So now let's just finish this. הגיעו לפרק, higiu le-perek, they came
to the first stitch, I think you would call that. Don't you
call that in poetry or in song, like the first, anyway they
would divide each פרק perek of תהילים, Tehillim, literally we call that
each chapter of תהילים, Tehillim, each פזמון פזמון pizmon pizmon different chapter,
as we're going to find out, as we know we say a
different שיר של יום, shir shel yom, they would divide... divided it
into thirds. So when they came to the first break of that
chapter, they תקעו, teku, they did another, not only with the לויים
Leviyim throughout the whole thing, they were singing with musical accompaniment, but
at when they took a little break when they did a break,
there was a break within the middle, then the כהנים Kohanim did
their תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah. וישתחוו העם Vayishtachavu ha'am one
minute, על כל פרק. al kol perek. וישתחוו העם Vayishtachavu ha'am and
the people bowed down. So again, as you imagine if the לויים
Leviyim are singing with their musical accompaniment, they're singing this chapter of
תהילים. Tehillim. They come to some little stopping point, a little pause,
which is they broke it up into thirds, so there's a little
pause in the middle. At that pause, then everybody else gets a
chance to participate. The כהנים Kohanim do their תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah
teruah tekiah, everybody who's there bows down, השתחויה. hishtachavayah. The trumpet players,
exactly, the ישראל Yisrael that's gathered there does a השתחויה. hishtachavayah. And
then they would do that for they would do that three times,
על כל פרק תקיעה. al kol perek tekiah. But they had the
יין yayin on the נסוך, nisuch, right? No, now it's during, meaning
they start singing when he's about to, and then it's happening at
the same it's happening simultaneously, concurrently. So let me just finish. Right,
right, I assume they tried to time it so that he would
finish the pouring when they would finish their singing. Okay, על כל
פרק תקיעה, al kol perek tekiah, with every break there would be
this תקיעה, tekiah, ועל כל תקיעה, ve'al kol tekiah, and whenever the
כהנים Kohanim were doing their תקיעה, tekiah, השתחויה, hishtachavayah, the people would
bow down. זהו סדר התמיד לעבודת בית אלוהינו יהי רצון שיבנה במהרה
בימינו אמן. Zeh'u seder hatamid la'avodat beit eloheinu yehi ratzon sheyibaneh bimeherah
beyameinu amen. That's a very nice way of ending, listen to the
way it ends. This is the way the קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid
was brought in the house of our God, may it be God's
will that it should be speedily built in our days. And then
you have another משנה. Mishna. I don't know what oh, because presumably
because it was written after the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit. Or I
mean I guess you could imagine that that line was inserted after
the חורבן הבית. Churban HaBayit. We are going to actually I will
talk to you when we get to מדות Middot in a few
minutes about who the גמרא Gemara thinks was the author of at
least מדות, Middot, but presumably of תמיד Tamid as well. The גמרא
Gemara actually thinks that it was somebody who lived at that time.
Okay, and we'll talk about that when we get to that גמרא.
Gemara. Now I want to say two things here about and then
we'll leave the last thing. The two things I want to say
is number one about the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah and
the חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. So they would do there's other places the גמרא
Gemara says that they would do a תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah
tekiah when they opened the gate, they'd do a תקיעה תרועה תקיעה
tekiah teruah tekiah for the קרבנות, korbanot, they would do it for
the קרבנות ציבור. korbanot tzibur. By the way, the לויים Leviyim singing,
they wouldn't sing by every individual's קרבן, korban, it would be for
the קרבנות ציבור. korbanot tzibur. Primarily actually it would be for the
תמיד של שחר Tamid shel Shachar and תמיד של בין הערביים, Tamid
shel Bein Ha'arbayim, but they would do and that's also when they
would do the תקיעה תרועה תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiahs, and they would
do nine on the תמיד של שחר, Tamid shel Shachar, nine של
בין הערביים. shel Bein Ha'arbayim. Now of course that immediately evokes the
פסוקים psukim and the חצוצרות chatzotzrot in במדבר, Bamidbar, which is וביום
שמחתכם ובמועדיכם ובראשי חדשיכם ותקעתם בחצצרת על עלתיכם ועל זבחי שלמיכם, Uveyom
simchatchem uvemoadeichem uverashei chodsheichem utekatem bachtzotzrot al oloteichem veal zivchei shalmeichem, blow
the חצוצרות. chatzotzrot. So according to all basically everybody agrees that the
blowing of the חצוצרות chatzotzrot on the מוספים Musafim of a רגל
Regel and ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh is from the פסוק, pasuk, it's
a מצוה mitzvah from the תורה. Torah. Because it says ובמועדיכם ובראשי
חדשיכם. uvemoadeichem uverashei chodsheichem. So and many of the מוני מצוות monei
mitzvot including the רמב"ם Rambam have that as a separate one of
the תרי"ג מצוות. taryag mitzvot. Some take it as separate מצוות, mitzvot,
part of עבודת הקרבנות. avodat hakorbanot. But anyway, but that's when it's
the רגל. Regel. But we also have it done at the תמיד.
Tamid. So there is a ספרי Sifrei ספרא Sifra ספרי Sifrei anyway
that learns it out from the פסוק pasuk that says ובמועדיכם. uvemoadeichem.
That מועד moed doesn't just mean on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but
it means anything that is במועדו, bemoado, a fixed time, which includes
the תמיד, Tamid, and therefore says that according to that, even the
blowing on the תמיד Tamid is דאורייתא, De'oraita, and a number of
ראשונים Rishonim believe that. And now we're getting the תמיד Tamid and
the מוספים, Musafim, what we're basically getting is pretty much all the
קרבנות ציבור. korbanot tzibur. So how about קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, which
is sort of a קרבן ציבור, korban tzibur, not exactly קרבן ציבור.
korban tzibur. So believe it or not, by the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach as well, there's a תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah tekiah when
that was being brought, the people sort of bring it en masse.
So but everybody had their individual ones, and also there's a ספרי
Sifrei that says זבחי שלמיכם zivchei shalmeichem is coming to include קרבן
פסח. Korban Pesach. So they would do these תקיעות תרועות תקיעות teki'ot
teru'ot teki'ot by קרבנות ציבור korbanot tzibur based on the פסוקים. psukim.
Clearly it was דאורייתא De'oraita on the by the מועדים, moadim, but
presumably according to many it was דאורייתא De'oraita as well by the
תמיד. Tamid. That's one thing. Now the other thing I wanted to
point out was, okay, when did the people come in? That's not
discussed at all. And I did some research yesterday trying to find
out if it's explicit anywhere when they opened up the main gate,
and it is not. What is clear here is that the people
were definitely there by the time they were doing the ניסוך היין.
nisuch hayayin. Not only that, presumably if there was a ברכת כהנים
Birkat Kohanim right before, they were there at least a few minutes
before that for the ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim. Now what is clear
even more than that is when talks about the תקיעות teki'ot that
they would do in the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it says they
did three תקיעות teki'ot for פתיחת השערים, ptichat hashearim, opening gates, and
three nine for the קרבנות, korbanot, as we said that they did
three times, but each time not the ones they did before. doesn't
just mean the gate of the היכל, Heichal, it means the gate
of the עזרה. Azarah. So that so they clearly let the people
in prior to the end of the קרבן תמיד, Korban Tamid, prior
to the pouring of the wine, prior presumably to ברכת כהנים, Birkas
Kohanim, but it never says exactly when. Now there's one of the
מפרשים Meforshim on the משנה, Mishna, the יכין ובועז Yachin U'Boaz תפארת
ישראל, Tiferes Yisrael, he assumes it was way back right after the
תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen and at the same time they opened up
the gate of the היכל, Heichal, the door of the היכל. Heichal.
But it's not said anywhere, he just assumes that. There is another
משנה Mishna by the way in יומא Yoma that says you know
when on the רגלים Regalim there were so many people that even
before the cock crowed you had the whole עזרה Azarah was filled
with ישראל. Yisrael. So that sounds like that idea that it was
right after the תרומת הדשן. Trumas Hadeshen. But first of all maybe
it means עזרת נשים. Ezras Nashim. If you want to say the
whole עזרה Azarah was filled with ישראל, Yisrael, it's not such a
big deal to say that this space was filled with ישראל. Yisrael.
But the other thing is and some מפרשים Meforshim say the תפארת
ישראל Tiferes Yisrael himself says that that was an exception. That in
order to get a lot of people there for the רגל, Regel,
maybe then you opened it up. You know what it is? Like
before Thanksgiving, right? Doors open at 4:00 AM. So maybe that was
an exception. So the fascinating thing is it's not explicit anywhere, which
often is fascinating because it shows, as we were saying, there's such
a high level of detail but it's from the perspective of the
כהנים. Kohanim. You never get the people's perspective here, right? So we
don't even know when they opened up the doors. We know it
was sometime before they finished the תמיד Tamid presumably at sometime before
the ברכת כהנים. Birkas Kohanim. But exactly when is never actually spelled
out. I really tried to find it yesterday and I was so
you could sort of guestimate, but it's never exactly explicit. So let's
just finish the מסכת. Masechet. השיר שהיו הלויים אומרים במקדש. Hashir shehayu
HaLevi'im omrim baMikdash. So people might be familiar with this, we say
it on שבת, Shabbos, right? The שיר shir right after the פיטום
הקטורת. Pitum Haketores. Now you know why you say it after the
פיטום הקטורת, Pitum Haketores, right? You bring the קטורת, Kettores, then you
finish the תמיד, Tamid, and then you say the שיר של יום,
Shir Shel Yom, right? So the שיר shir that לויים Levi'im would
say. By the way, you know that some people, people have the
מנהג minhag that on שבת Shabbos you say the שיר של יום
Shir Shel Yom before you take out the תורה, Torah, not at
the end of דאווען. davening. Why? Because it came with the תמיד
של שחר. Tamid Shel Shachar. By the end of דאווען, davening, you're
post מוסף. Musaf. The מוסף Musaf was the קרבן korban that came
afterwards. Okay, so some people do it later. Anyway back to השיר
שהיו הלויים. Hashir shehayu HaLevi'im. Oh and the גרא Gra says a
different says the שיר של יום Shir Shel Yom of the רגלים
Regalim on the רגל. Regel. Why do you say the normal one?
So I mean okay some things just become part of the liturgy,
they don't exactly follow. Anyway, השיר שהיו הלויים אומרים במקדש. Hashir shehayu
HaLevi'im omrim baMikdash. ביום הראשון היו אומרים לה' הארץ ומלואה תבל ויושבי
בה. Bayom harishon hayu omrim: L'Hashem ha'aretz umlo'ah, tevel v'yoshvei vah. That's
obvious, right? That's the day of creation, first day. So for God
is the entire earth. בשני היו אומרים גדול ה' ומהולל מאד בעיר
אלוקינו הר קדשו. Basheini hayu omrim: Gadol Hashem u'mihullal me'od b'ir Elokeinu
har kodsho. Now not exactly clear what that has to do with
the second day, which was the waters and the heavens. So okay
because those are amazing things to split the waters and גדול אלוקינו.
Gadol Elokeinu. I mean that's not so satisfying. There's the זוהר, Zohar,
I only know this because I read it in קהתי. Kehati. The
זוהר Zohar does what actually what's common, the רמב"ן Ramban does this
על התורה al haTorah as well, is compare the six days, רמב"ן
Ramban in בראשית, Bereishis, of creation to the concept of six thousand
years is the well the six thousand years and משיח Moshiach will
come in the seventh thousand in year six thousand, the seven thousandth
year. And then comparing the days of creation as symbolic for what
happened during that thousand-year period. So the second, so according to that,
why the reason they would say גדול ה' ומהולל מאד בעיר אלוקינו
הר קדשו Gadol Hashem u'mihullal me'od b'ir Elokeinu har kodsho because it's
the עיר אלוקינו ir Elokeinu and אברהם Avraham was 1948 of creation,
it's an easy year to remember. He was year 1948 from creation,
אברהם. Avraham. So he actually עקידת יצחק Akeidas Yitzchak and all of
that was within the towards the end of the second millennium and
that was the choosing of עיר אלוקינו ir Elokeinu like of הר
המוריה. Har HaMoriah. That's a little bit maybe. Okay, anyway בשלישי היו
אומרים, Bashelishi hayu omrim, the third one is easier. אלוקים נצב בעדת
אל בקרב אלוקים ישפוט. Elokim nitzav ba'adas Eil, b'kerev elokim yishpot. Because
the third one was that was that was the golden age, that
was מתן תורה, Matan Torah, going into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, the
first and second בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So that's אלוקים נצב בעדת,
Elokim nitzav ba'adas, God was sort of fully present with the Jewish
people. Okay this is all the זוהר. Zohar. ברביעי היו אומרים אל
נקמות ה' אל נקמות הופיע. Barevi'i hayu omrim: Eil nekamot Hashem, Eil
nekamot hofi'a. The next thousand years was the חורבן הבית. Churban Habayis.
Okay and was גלות. Galus. So that's a sense of God taking
judgment against His people. בחמישי היו אומרים הרנינו לאלוקים עוזנו הריעו לאלוקי
יעקב. Bachamishi hayu omrim: Harninu l'Elokim uzeinu, hari'u l'Elokei Yaakov. I'm trying
to remember what they connect that to. Oh I think also, yeah
yeah, also the sense that there was no בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
and therefore, oh this is interesting from the זוהר Zohar because if
you think about our ongoing conversation, it connects it to the idea
that if you have no בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, how do we
connect to God? Through prayer. So it's הרנינו Harninu Could have been
for the fourth out, could have been. Anyway, השם מלך גאות לבש,
Hashem malach geus lavesh, לבש השם עז התאזר, lavesh Hashem oz isazar,
so God will be king because with that is the you know
the six thousandth year is when we hope the משיח Moshiach will
come because if there's going to be and you know and it's
the you know and so this is the period of like rejuvenation
because actually שבת Shabbos is already we're into עולם הבא. olam haba.
So the sixth is השם מלך גאות לבש, Hashem malach geus lavesh,
God will you know will be the rebuilding of the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash or whatever and by the time you get to the
seventh, שבת, Shabbos, מזמור שיר ליום השבת. mizmor shir l'yom hashabas. Well,
first of all, that's just obvious in terms of פשט, pshat, שבת,
Shabbos, so you're saying מזמור שיר ליום השבת. mizmor shir l'yom hashabas.
שיר לעתיד לבוא, shir l'asid lavo, but here it actually connects it,
which gives sort of a nice, you know, strength to the זוהר
Zohar interpretation from before, ליום שכולו שבת ומנוחה לחיי העולמים. l'yom shekulo
shabbos u'menucha l'chayei ha'olamim. It's not just a שיר shir for שבת
Shabbos but it's a שיר shir for envisioning a perfect type of
a world. Okay, הדרן עלך פרק זמן שהן גדיל וסליקא מסכת תמיד.
hadran alach perek zman shehein gadil u'selika masechet tamid. So that was
a lot of fun. I just don't know why the little closure
came one משנה mishna too, too soon. And now we move on
to מסכת מדות, masechet middos, where there is no גמרא gemara and
the print is a little bit bigger. Okay, so let's take a
look at the top of ל''ד ע''א. lamed daled amud aleph. I'm
going to actually